<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<lesson title="Network Topologies" level="beginner">
  <objective>Define network topology and explain its importance</objective>
  <objective>Describe the five common network topologies</objective>
  <objective>Compare the advantages and disadvantages of each topology</objective>

  <definition term="Network Topology">
    The arrangement of nodes (computers, switches, routers) and connections (cables, wireless links) in a network. It describes both the physical layout and the logical flow of data.
  </definition>

  <example title="Bus Topology">
    All devices connect to a single shared cable (the "bus"). Data travels along the cable and is received by all devices, but only the intended recipient processes it.
    Advantage: Simple, inexpensive. Disadvantage: A single cable failure breaks the entire network.
  </example>

  <example title="Star Topology">
    All devices connect to a central hub or switch. This is the most common topology in modern LANs (home routers, office switches).
    Advantage: Easy to manage, failure of one device doesn't affect others. Disadvantage: Central hub is a single point of failure.
  </example>

  <example title="Ring Topology">
    Devices connect in a circular chain. Data travels in one direction around the ring.
    Advantage: Equal access for all nodes. Disadvantage: A single broken connection can disrupt the entire network.
  </example>

  <example title="Mesh Topology">
    Every device has a dedicated connection to every other device. Used in WANs and critical infrastructure.
    Advantage: Highly redundant, no single point of failure. Disadvantage: Expensive, complex cabling.
  </example>

  <example title="Hybrid Topology">
    A combination of two or more topologies (e.g., a star-bus or star-ring). Most real-world networks are hybrid topologies.
  </example>

  <note type="tip">
    For modern enterprise networks, star topology (with a central managed switch) is the standard choice for LANs. Mesh topology is used in the internet's core routing infrastructure.
  </note>

  <diagram alt="Network Topology Comparison" caption="Common network topologies">
Bus:    A---B---C---D---E  (single cable)
Star:       A
           /|\
          B-S-C            (S = Switch/Hub)
           \|/
            D
Ring:   A--B--C--D--A     (circular)
Mesh:   A---B
        |\ /|
        | X |              (every node connected to every other)
        |/ \|
        C---D
  </diagram>

  <quiz title="Topology Quiz">
    <question type="multiple-choice" text="Which topology provides the highest level of redundancy?">
      <answer correct="false">Bus</answer>
      <answer correct="false">Star</answer>
      <answer correct="false">Ring</answer>
      <answer correct="true">Mesh</answer>
    </question>
    <question type="true-false" text="In a star topology, if the central switch fails, all network communication stops.">
      <answer correct="true">True</answer>
      <answer correct="false">False</answer>
    </question>
  </quiz>

  <exercise difficulty="easy">
    Draw a diagram of a small office network with 8 computers, 1 switch, and 1 router.
    What topology does this represent? What would happen if the switch failed?
  </exercise>

  <summary>
    <item>Network topology describes how devices are physically and logically connected</item>
    <item>Bus: Simple but fragile; Star: Most common, central switch; Ring: Circular path</item>
    <item>Mesh: Maximum redundancy, used in WANs; Hybrid: Real-world combination</item>
    <item>Star topology dominates modern LANs; mesh is used in critical infrastructure</item>
  </summary>
</lesson>
