<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<lesson title="HTTP and HTTPS" level="intermediate">
  <objective>Describe the HTTP request/response cycle</objective>
  <objective>Identify common HTTP methods, status codes, and headers</objective>
  <objective>Explain how HTTPS uses TLS to provide security</objective>

  <definition term="HTTP (HyperText Transfer Protocol)">
    An application-layer protocol that defines how clients (browsers) and servers communicate to transfer web content. HTTP is stateless — each request is independent.
  </definition>

  <note type="info">
    HTTP typically uses port 80. HTTPS (HTTP Secure) uses port 443 and encrypts all communication using TLS (Transport Layer Security).
  </note>

  <example title="HTTP Request/Response Cycle">
    1. You type https://www.example.com in your browser
    2. Browser performs DNS lookup to get the server's IP
    3. Browser establishes a TCP connection (port 443 for HTTPS)
    4. TLS handshake encrypts the connection
    5. Browser sends an HTTP GET request
    6. Server processes the request and sends an HTTP response
    7. Browser renders the HTML response
  </example>

  <codeblock language="http">
GET /index.html HTTP/1.1
Host: www.example.com
Accept: text/html,application/xhtml+xml
User-Agent: Mozilla/5.0 (Windows NT 10.0; Win64; x64)
Connection: keep-alive

HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Content-Type: text/html; charset=UTF-8
Content-Length: 1256
Cache-Control: max-age=3600

&lt;html&gt;...&lt;/html&gt;
  </codeblock>

  <definition term="HTTP Methods">
    GET: Retrieve a resource (read-only, idempotent)
    POST: Submit data to create a resource
    PUT: Replace a resource entirely
    PATCH: Partially update a resource
    DELETE: Remove a resource
    HEAD: Like GET but returns only headers
    OPTIONS: Query available methods
  </definition>

  <definition term="HTTP Status Codes">
    1xx — Informational (100 Continue)
    2xx — Success (200 OK, 201 Created, 204 No Content)
    3xx — Redirection (301 Moved Permanently, 302 Found)
    4xx — Client Error (400 Bad Request, 401 Unauthorized, 403 Forbidden, 404 Not Found)
    5xx — Server Error (500 Internal Server Error, 503 Service Unavailable)
  </definition>

  <note type="tip">
    A quick way to remember status codes: 2=happy (success), 4=your fault (client error), 5=our fault (server error).
  </note>

  <definition term="HTTPS and TLS">
    HTTPS wraps HTTP in TLS (Transport Layer Security). TLS provides:
    - Encryption: Data cannot be read by eavesdroppers
    - Authentication: Server presents a certificate to prove its identity
    - Integrity: Data cannot be tampered with in transit
  </definition>

  <example title="TLS Handshake (Simplified)">
    1. Client Hello: Browser sends supported TLS versions and cipher suites
    2. Server Hello: Server selects cipher suite, sends its certificate
    3. Certificate Verification: Browser verifies the certificate with a trusted CA
    4. Key Exchange: Both sides compute a shared secret key
    5. Finished: Both sides confirm encryption is active
    All subsequent HTTP data is encrypted with the negotiated key.
  </example>

  <note type="warning">
    Never send sensitive data (passwords, credit cards) over plain HTTP. Always ensure your site uses HTTPS with a valid certificate. Look for the padlock icon in the browser.
  </note>

  <quiz title="HTTP and HTTPS Quiz">
    <question type="multiple-choice" text="Which HTTP status code indicates a successful request?">
      <answer correct="true">200</answer>
      <answer correct="false">301</answer>
      <answer correct="false">404</answer>
      <answer correct="false">500</answer>
    </question>
    <question type="multiple-choice" text="Which port does HTTPS use by default?">
      <answer correct="false">80</answer>
      <answer correct="true">443</answer>
      <answer correct="false">8080</answer>
      <answer correct="false">8443</answer>
    </question>
    <question type="multiple-choice" text="Which HTTP method is used to retrieve a web page?">
      <answer correct="true">GET</answer>
      <answer correct="false">POST</answer>
      <answer correct="false">PUT</answer>
      <answer correct="false">DELETE</answer>
    </question>
    <question type="short-answer" text="What does TLS stand for and what does it provide?">
      <answer correct="true">Transport Layer Security — provides encryption, authentication, and data integrity for HTTPS connections</answer>
    </question>
  </quiz>

  <exercise difficulty="hard">
    Using your browser's Developer Tools (F12 → Network tab):
    (a) Visit any HTTPS website and inspect the request/response headers
    (b) Identify the HTTP method, status code, and content-type
    (c) Click on the security padlock and examine the TLS certificate details
    (d) Find at least 3 different HTTP response headers and explain their purpose
  </exercise>

  <summary>
    <item>HTTP is a stateless application-layer protocol for transferring web content</item>
    <item>HTTP methods: GET (read), POST (create), PUT/PATCH (update), DELETE (remove)</item>
    <item>Status codes: 2xx=success, 3xx=redirect, 4xx=client error, 5xx=server error</item>
    <item>HTTPS = HTTP + TLS encryption; uses port 443; provides encryption, auth, and integrity</item>
    <item>Always use HTTPS for any site handling sensitive data</item>
  </summary>
</lesson>
